Guide to the Ernie O'Malley Papers AIA.060
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I. Works, 1924-1956, undated
  - Subseries IA. Ernie O'Malley
    - Raids and Rallies: Radio Eireann address as published in The Sunday Press, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Raids and Rallies: manuscript (handwritten), circa 1951-1956 (Box 2, Folder 7A)
    - Raids and Rallies: typescript draft, circa 1951-1956 (Box 2, Folder 7B)
    - Raids and Rallies: typescript, circa 1951-1956 (Box 2, Folder 7C)
    - Raids and Rallies: typed drafts (I), circa 1951-1956 (Box 2, Folder 7D)
    - Raids and Rallies: typed drafts (I), circa 1951-1956 (Box 44, Folder 7E)
    - Raids and Rallies: Correspondence, 1955 (Box 44, Folder 7F)
    - Raids and Rallies: Notes from Publisher, circa 1955 (Box 44, Folder 7G)
    - Raids and Rallies: Notes for Publication [Cormac O'Malley], circa 1973 (Box 44, Folder 7H)
    - "Raid": unfinished short story, mansucript; fragile, circa 1934-1935 (Box 44, Folder 8)
    - "Renaissance," La France Libre: draft manuscript; typed version in French, 1946-1947 (Box 44, Folder 9)
      Writing by Ernie O'Malley concerning Irish neutrality during World War I and Irish reaction to this position.
    - "San Mareno Letters" manuscript, 1927 (Box 44, Folder 10)
      Series of satirical letters written by Ernie O'Malley concerning Irish politics while he was a member of parliament.
    - Sean Connolly: handwritten drafts, 1951-1953 (Box 40, Folder 14)
    - Sean Connolly: original typescript for biography; annotations, circa 1952 (Box 44, Folder 11)
      Subsequently published as Rising Out: Sean Connolly of Longford, 1890-1921 by Ernie O'Malley, edited by Cormac O'Malley, University College Dublin Press, 2007.
    - Sean Connolly: typescripts, 1951-1953 (Box 40, Folder 15)
    - Sean Connolly: correspondence, 1952 (Box 44, Folder 12)
      See also Outgoing Correspondence: Citkowitz.
    - Sean Connolly: notebook, circa 1952 (Box 44, Folder 13)
      Notes on Connolly in preparation for lectures and articles on the War of Independence. Later used for biography on Connolly and Raids and Rallies.
    - Speech for Oct 28: Mission to the United States to raise funds for the Irish Press, manuscript, 1928 (Box 44, Folder 14)
      Speech by Ernie O'Malley written on Dail Eireann stationary concerning his mission to the United States as ordered by Eamon de Valera: to raise funds to establish the Irish Press as an independent newspaper in Ireland.
    - Short Story manuscript, untitled: Begins with "Is family enough ...", circa 1934-1935 (Box 44, Folder 15)
    - "Sullivan Skin the Mule" short story, manuscript, 1934-1935 (Box 44, Folder 16)
    - Short story, untitled: Begins with "Seated at a table away from the bar..." (three versions), circa 1934-1935 (Box 44, Folder 17)
    - Short story: Begins with "Words step into life" (three drafts, manuscript), circa 1934-1935 (Box 44, Folder 18)
    - "The Sack of Mallow" essay, Ireland To-Day (inscribed to COM), Sep 1936 (Box 44, Folder 19)
      Published as an essay in Ireland Today and On Another Man's Wound in 1936. Dedicated to Cormac O'Malley by the son of James L. Donovan in 1999.
    - The Singing Flame manuscript; EOM's second autobiography; 1921-1924, circa 1930-1935 (Box 44, Folder 20)
    - The Singing Flame: handwritten manuscript draft (I), circa 1930-1935 (Box 40, Folder 16)
    - The Singing Flame: handwritten manuscript draft (II), circa 1930-1935 (Box 40, Folder 17)
    - The Singing Flame (Truce, Four Courts) manuscript, partial ending, circa 1930-1935 (Box 44, Folder 21)
    - The Singing Flame typescript (original title: Ireland); "Dedicated to Ireland the ever-living and her dead sons", circa 1930-1935 (Box 44, Folder 22)
    - The Singing Flame manuscript, typescript, with annotations, undated (Box 44, Folder 23)
    - The Singing Flame typescript, corrections, partial, undated (Box 44, Folder 24)
    - The Singing Flame typescript, annotated, corrections, partial, undated (Box 45, Folder 25)
    - The Singing Flame: American typescript, Jul-Nov 1922 (Box 40, Folder 18)
    - "Traditions in Mexican Art" essay and drafts; published in The Listener, 1946-1947 (Box 45, Folder 26)
    - "Weed of Ten Thousand Years": short story, undated (Box 40, Folder 19)
    - Untitled: Begins with "And you're no good; you have let us down ... " manuscript, [1933] (Box 45, Folder 27)
    - Untitled: Begins with "As soon as the men who fought in Easter week ... " typescript, circa 1940-1945 (Box 45, Folder 28)
    - Untitled: Begins with "Do we ever get outside of ourselves ... " manuscript, one page, fragile, circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 29)
    - Untitled: Begins with "Easter Began For Us...", circa 1930-1931 (Box 40, Folder 20)
    - Untitled: Begins with "Five girls from Monterey in Saltillo ... " manuscript, onionskin, circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 30)
    - Untitled: Begins with "Harvard archeologists are curious ... " manuscript, typesript, circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 31)
    - Untitled: Begins with "He rubbed his ... " manuscript, circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 32)
    - Untitled: Begins with "I got tired of you speak pretty good English ..." manuscript, circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 33)
    - Untitled: Begins with "I'm going home soon and I'll be glad of it ..." two separate drafts, manuscript, typescript, circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 34)
    - Untitled: Begins with "The Icelandic settlement was a .... " manuscript, circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 35)
    - Untitled: Begins with "In Mexico there has been a continuous tradition ..." manuscript, circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 36)
    - Untitled: Begins with "In the Gaelic State there was no drama ... " manuscript, circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 37)
    - Untitled: Begins with "Indeed", undated (Box 40, Folder 21)
    - Untitled: Begins with "Ireland had always imported manufactured ... " manuscript, typescript, 1947 (Box 45, Folder 38)
    - Untitled: Begins with "The Irish dramatic movement is a separate ... ", circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 39)
    - Untitled: Begins with "Josquin de Pres was born in ... " typescript, circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 40)
    - Untitled: Begins with "Karl Swartz reached for his tobacco ... " manuscript; typescript (3 drafts), circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 41)
    - Untitled: Begins with "Lieutenant Frank O'Hara tried to strike a match ... " manuscript, circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 42)
    - Untitled: Begins with "Michael Hegarty was a Corkman ... " manuscript, circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 43)
    - Untitled: Begins with "Michael O'Malley was born and bred ... " manuscript, circa 1946 (Box 45, Folder 44)
    - Untitled: Begins with "Most people see the world by arriving ... " manuscript, circa 1946 (Box 45, Folder 45)
    - Untitled: Begins with "The Pounding Drum...", circa 1930-1931 (Box 40, Folder 22)
    - Untitled: Begins with "The Senior Officers...", undated (Box 40, Folder 23)
    - Untitled: Begins with "Sheila and Sean walk through the trees ... " manuscript, circa 1946 (Box 45, Folder 46)
    - Untitled: Begins with "Somers shifted his feet and smiled ... " typescript, circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 47)
    - Untitled: Begins with "The South...", circa 1930-1931 (Box 40, Folder 24)
    - Untitled: Begins with "Strictly Observed...", circa 1930-1931 (Box 40, Folder 25)
    - Untitled: Begins with "Talking of dreams, Von Holtz said ... " typescript, two copies, circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 48)
    - Untitled: Begins with "The Unfortunate burro I thought! ... " typescript, circa 1934-1935 (Box 45, Folder 49)
    - Untitled: Begins with "The word Indian ... " manuscript, circa 1946 (Box 45, Folder 50)
  - Subseries IB. Other Writers
    - Ballads: Irish, manuscript, typescript, 1916-1923 (Box 45, Folder 51)
      Printed ballad sheets, including many by PJ K O'Reilly (Wrap the Green Flag Round Me), JJ Walsh (The Flag on the GPO 1916), Peader Kearney (Soldier's Song), Thomas Ashe (Poem), Phil O'Neill (Remember Ashe and Men of Easter Week), Padraig de Brun (In Memory of O'Connor, Mellows, McKelvey and Barret), and Captain Jim Moran (High Upon the Gallows Tree and General Monroe).
    - Ballads: Irish, originals and typescript by EOM, 1954-1956 (Box 45, Folder 52)
    - Ballads: Irish; manuscript, typescript, handbills, 1933-1935, undated (Box 45, Folder 53)
    - Ballads: American, sea shanties; typescript, some manuscript, undated (Box 45, Folder 54)
    - Ballads: Irish (76 items), 1917-1985 (Box 45, Folder 55)
    - Ballads: Irish, circa 1918-1939 (Box 45, Folder 56)
    - Ballads: Irish, circa 1928-1956 (Box 45, Folder 57)
    - Ballads: New Mexico, Frank S. Gutierrez, Ranchos de Taos, circa 1929 (Box 45, Folder 58)
    - Crane, Hart - poems, 1931, undated (Box 45, Folder 59)
    - Greene, Graham: "A Few Pipes", typescript, annotations, 1953-1954 (Box 45, Folder 60)
    - Livesy, Edward: "The Walls are Down: Portrait of a Kleptomaniac"; BBC radio script, Jul 4, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - MacDonagh, Don: "The Races of Castlebar" typescript with annotations, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Poems (to later comprise Ernie O'Malley private anthology), circa 1932-1935 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Poems (71); manuscript, typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Poems (74); manuscript, typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Poems: Irish (215): I, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Poems: Irish (215): II, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Poems: Irish (215): III, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Poems: Final version of anthology (200): I, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Poems: Final version of anthology (200): II, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Poems: Final version of anthology (200): III, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Poems: Final version of anthology (200): IV, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Poems: Final version of anthology (200): V, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Rowan, Martin "The Inauguration of Alphonsus O'Reilly, D.C." typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Poems: cut out of various publications, undated (Box 3, Folder 14A)
    - Reviews and editorials: cut out of various publications, undated (Box 3, Folder 14B)
- Series II. Correspondence: Incoming, 1922-1956
  Files are arranged alphabetically by surname.
  Included are letters, telegrams, greeting cards and postcards sent to Ernie O'Malley between the years of 1922 and 1956. The correspondence in this series is of a personal nature, detailing O'Malley's friendships and associations, as well as, a business nature documenting O'Malley's dealings with publishers, solicitors, and government agencies. Throughout the course of his life O'Malley maintained friendships with notable artists, poets and writers in both Ireland and the United States. Of special interest are the postcards and letters sent to O'Malley while he was imprisoned at Kilmainham Jail and Curragh Camp during the Irish Civil War in 1923 and 1924.
  A limited number of items in this series are photocopies received from various universities, institutions, or private family collections at the request of Cormac O'Malley, Ernie O'Malley's youngest son. Throughout the course of research on his father Cormac O'Malley also transcribed a considerable number of the letters written by Ernie O'Malley. Those transcriptions have been included with the original or photocopy when available.
  - Indices to Correspondence: Incoming (2 and 2A), 2010 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Aiken, Frank, 1928-1935; cuid36532 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Scope and Contents
    This correspondence consists of 13 pages.
  - Ames, Elizabeth (Executive Director of Yaddo Foundation), 1932; cuid36533 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    This correspondence consists of 4 pages.
  - Ampleforth College, York England (where Cathal and Cormac will attend), 1946-1956; cuid36534 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    This correspondence consists of 5 pages.
  - Barton, Daa (Dulcibella), 1945-1947, undated; cuid36535 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    This correspondence consists of 6 pages.
  - British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC), 1947-1983; cuid36536 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    This correspondence consists of 19 pages.
  - Beckett, Samuel, autograph letter signed, 1947, 1955; cuid36537 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Bernard, A., circa 1925, undated; cuid36538 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    This correspondence consists of 2 pages.
  - [Blainthen ni B] to Ernie O'Malley in jail, 1924; cuid36539 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    This correspondence consists of 7 pages.
  - Brady, Frank (Frances), 1924; cuid36540 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    This correspondence consists of 3 pages.
  - Brady, James A., Jan 29, 1952; cuid36541 (Box 3, Folder 24A)
  - Brady, Kathleen (Kay; sister of Frances), 1924-1944; cuid36542 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    This correspondence consists of 14 pages.
  - Brady (Kay or Frank?) to Ernie O'Malley in jail, 1923; cuid36543 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Breen, Dan, 1936; cuid36544 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Brennan, Francis Joseph (Jr.), Sep 4, 1955; cuid36545 (Box 3, Folder 27A)
    This correspondence consists of 1 page.
  - Brennan, Robert (Bob) [empty], 1924; cuid36546 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Brett, Dorothy (letter regarding death of D.H. Lawrence; Taos, New Mexico), 1930, undated; cuid36547 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    This correspondence consists of 8 pages.
  - Brown, Paddy [Podraig de Brun), President, University College Galway, 1944-1947; cuid36548 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Brown, Sheila (Random House), 1948; cuid36549 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Bureau of Military History, Nov 13, 1951; cuid36550 (Box 3, Folder 31A)
  - Burke-Sheridan, Margaret (opera singer, Co. Mayo), 1936; cuid36551 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Burrishoole Lodge, Newport, Co. Mayo (residence), 1943-1948; cuid36552 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    This correspondence consists of 32 pages.
  - Childers, Mary Alden Osgood (Molly; Mrs. Erskine Childers), 1924, 1936; cuid36553 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Citkowitz, Israel (composer), 1952; cuid36554 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Citkowitz-Liber, Rebecca (Mrs. Armour Liber), 1946-1951; cuid36555 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    This correspondence consists of 16 pages.
  - Clurman, Harold (theatre critic and director), circa 1952; cuid36556 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Coffey, Brian, 1945; cuid36557 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Cole, Lois Dwight (MacMillan Company), 1933; cuid36558 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Coughlan, Madge, Oct 18, 1945; cuid36559 (Box 3, Folder 39A)
  - Counahan, Maire ni (to EOM in jail), 1924; cuid36560 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Craig, Maurice, Feb 28, 1948; cuid36561 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Crane, Hart, 1931; cuid36562 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    This correspondence consists of 10 pages.
  - Crowe E[ileen], 1932, 1937; cuid36563 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Crowley, Dan, Jul 28, 1932; cuid36564 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Curran, Cornelius P. (C.P.), 1951-1956; cuid36565 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Davidson, Bob, 1932; cuid36566 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Davis, Chester C. (Simpson, Thatcher & Bartlett- Helen Hooker's lawyer), 1953-1953; cuid36567 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Delemer, C., circa 1925; cuid36568 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Department of Defence, 1940-1941; cuid36569 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - DeValera, Eamon, autograph letter signed, 1928; cuid36570 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Dolan, Sister Mary Scholastica, Sligo, 1932, 1936; cuid36571 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Doyle, Andy (IRA), Tipperary, 1945, undated; cuid36572 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Duffy, Luke, Sep 12, 1955; cuid36573 (Box 3, Folder 52A)
  - Egan-Gill, Molly, 1936; cuid36574 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - [F.S.] unknown, 1950; cuid36575 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Fitzgerald, Mabel (wife of Minister of Foreign Affairs), 1923; cuid36576 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Fitzgerald, Thomas Garrett, Sep 18, 1955; cuid36577 (Box 3, Folder 55A)
  - Ford, John, 1950-1953; cuid36578 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Frost, Sheila (artist), circa 1945; cuid36579 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Gallagher, Frank (author), 1929, 1936; cuid36580 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Gaynor, Sean, Sep 19, 1955; cuid36581 (Box 3, Folder 58A)
  - Gerrard, Thomas, 1956; cuid36582 (Box 3, Folder 58B)
  - Gilmore, George, Nov 30, 1936; cuid36583 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Goddard, Theodora (artist), circa 1932-1934; cuid36584 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    This correspondence consists of 35 pages.
  - Golden, Helen Merriam (American actress), circa 1930-1940; cuid36585 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Golden-Sax, Eithne, 1932-1955; cuid36586 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    This correspondence consists of 17 pages.
  - [Gongane, Coanin] unknown, Aug 12, 1947; cuid36587 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Greene, Graham (letters of introduction for Ernie O'Malley to Eyre & Spottiswoode Publishers, Ltd, London), May 1947; cuid36588 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Halligan-Clarke, Sunny (Mrs. Michael Clarke), 1938-1945; cuid36589 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    This correspondence consists of 9 pages.
  - Hanlon, Jack (artist, priest), 1946; cuid36590 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Harcourt, Alfred (Harcourt, Brace Co.), 1929-1933; cuid36591 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Heller, Clemens (Salzburg Seminar in American Studies), 1948; cuid36592 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Henry, Francois (University College Dublin), 1938-1939; cuid36593 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Herbert, Robert (Bob) Limerick Public Library, 1945-1956; cuid36594 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    This correspondence consists of 39 pages.
  - Hone, Eve (artist), 1943-19950; cuid36595 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Howe, Mariana (cabinet maker), 1930; cuid36596 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Hughes, John T. (lawyer), 1932-1939; cuid36597 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Humphreys, Sigle (Sheila, Mrs. Donal O'Donoghue), Apr 5, 1932; cuid36598 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Irish Academy of Letters, 1937-1950, 2005; cuid36599 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    This correspondence consists of 25 pages.
  - Irish Central Bureau, 1926; cuid36600 (Box 4, Folder 8A)
  - Jack B. Yeats National Loan Exhibition Committee, 1945-1946; cuid36601 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Jeffers, Una (Mrs. Robinson Jeffers), 1930; cuid36602 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Johnson, Walter Willard "Spud" (includes copy of ballad "Buck Dunton and the Desparado"), 1930; cuid36603 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Jellety, Bay (sister of Maine; artist), Sep 7, 1947; cuid36604 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Jooss, Kurth (German modern dancer), Oct 21, 1941; cuid36605 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Kelleher, John V. (Harvard University), 1948; cuid36606 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Kelly, Grace V. (journalist), 1929; cuid36607 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Kennedy, Frank, Dec 3, 1943; cuid36608 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Kerrigan, Georgette, Dr. Sarsfield Kerrigan, 1946-1957; cuid36609 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Kerrigan, Mimi (daughter of Georgette), Dec 1946; cuid36610 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Kronenberger, Louis (Alfred A. Knopf), 1934; cuid36611 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Laverty, Maura (author/playwright), 1947-1951; cuid36612 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - le Brocquy, Louis (artist; mother Sybil le Brocquy), 1946-1951; cuid36613 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    This correspondence consists of 21 pages.
  - Leach, Henry G. (The Forum), 1935; cuid36614 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Leighton, Geroge R. (Harper's), 1932; cuid36615 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Leventhal, Con (Professor, Trinity College), Feb 7, 1944; cuid36616 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Little, Con W., Jan 5, 1941; cuid36617 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Loughnane, Anne, 1929; cuid36618 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - [MJ] (unknown); Mae Tobin, Limerick; to Ernie O'Malley in Hare Park Jail, Ju 10, 1924; cuid36619 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Macardle, Dorothy (author), May 22, 1936; cuid36620 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - MacCarville, Eileen McGrane (Professor of English, UCD), Jul 8, 1942; cuid36621 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - MacGreevy, Thomas (poet, author, Director National Gallery), 1940, 1947; cuid36622 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - MacManus, M.J. (Editor, Irish Press), 1936-1937; cuid36623 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    This correspondence consists of 12 pages.
  - MacNiece, Heidi and Louis, 1947-1949; cuid36624 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    This correspondence consists of 13pages.
  - Mayer, Therese (La France Libre), 1947-1950; cuid36625 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    This correspondence consists of 15 pages.
  - McCrossen, Helen (Mrs. Preston McGrassen), 1930; cuid36626 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - McDonnell, Capt. P.J., Mar 11, 1956; cuid36627 (Box 4, Folder 35A)
  - McGlynn, Michael G. (McGlynn Travel Bureau), 1933; cuid36628 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - McGrail, Jean (sculptor and travel writer), 1955; cuid36629 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    This correspondence consists of 23 pages.
  - McGrath, Kieran, Dec 23, 1947; cuid36630 (Box 4, Folder 37A)
  - McGuinness, Norah (artist), 1936; cuid36631 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - McHugh, Roger (UCD Dramatic Society; Professor of English), 1945; cuid36632 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - McMahon, Bryan (storyteller, author), 1947-1952; cuid36633 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - McSwiney, Mary (sister of Terence), Nov 28, 1936; cuid36634 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Mellquist, Jerome (art critic and friend from Yaddo), Sep 2, 1932; cuid36635 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Millburn, George, 1932-1933; cuid36636 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    This correspondence consists of 20 pages.
  - Miller, Otto (Wick Miller Soutwest Indian Crafts, San Ysidro, NM), 1932; cuid36637 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Mooney, Ria (actress), Nov 1, 1943; cuid36638 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Moore, Owen (military comrade), Oct 30, 1928; cuid36639 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Murphy, Delia (Mrs. T.J. McKiernan), 1941; cuid36640 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Murphy, Fr. Miceal (Michael), 1946-1948; cuid36641 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Murphy, Maigread (Mrs. Seamus Murphy), 1951-1952; cuid36642 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - [Nib, E.] (unknown) to Ernie O'Malley in jail, Jun 10, 1924; cuid36643 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Nolan, Dan (Editor, The Kerryman), 1952; cuid36644 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Noyk, Michael (solicitor for Ernie O'Malley; includes letter from Sean MacBride in re O'Mally v O'Mally), 1946-1974; cuid36645 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    This correspondence consists of 29 pages.
  - O'Broichain, Eoin (University Cork Dublin Democratic Society), Mar 19, 1929; cuid36646 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - O'Donnell, Peadar (Editor, The Bel l), 1947-1951; cuid36647 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - O'Donoghue, Florrie, Oct 16, 1945; cuid36648 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - O'Donovan, James L., 1923, 1936-1937; cuid36649 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - O'Faolain, Sean (author), 1939-1947; cuid36650 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - O'Flaherty, Liam (author), Jul 16, 1939; cuid36651 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - O'Laoighaire, LIam (Irish Film Society), 1937; cuid36652 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - O'Riann, Proinnsius, 1932-1933; cuid36653 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - O'Sullivan, Seamus (Editor, Dublin Magazine), 1940, 1947; cuid36654 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - O'Sullivan, Sean (artist), 1942-1944; cuid36655 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Otis, Raymond (Writers' Editions), 1935; cuid36656 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Piper, John (English painter), Feb 19, 1946; cuid36657 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Poetry Magazine (Chicago) (item from Chicago archives, photocopy), undated; cuid36658 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - [Proinnsias] (Frank, unknown), Fr., circa 1924; cuid36659 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Quinn [Frank], 1930; cuid36660 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Radio Eireann (includes correspondence from Francis McManus), 1937-1952; cuid36661 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Rakoczi, Basil (artist; leader White Stag School of Art, Ireland, 1940-1947), 1945; cuid36662 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Raleigh, John and Beatrice, 1944, 1948; cuid36663 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Raleigh, Peggy (Ernie O'Malley's goddaughter; daughter of John Raleigh) [no page 2], May 1945; cuid36664 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Reid, Nano, Dec 8, 1945; cuid36665 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Reilly, Tommy, Mar 31, 1952; cuid36666 (Box 4, Folder 72A)
  - ni Riann, Mairin Bean (Mrs. James Ryan), Jun 13, 1929; cuid36667 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Riardon, Eileen, circa 1940-1950; cuid36668 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Rich & Cowan Publishers and Exporters, 1936-1951; cuid36669 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    This correspondence consists of 48 pages.
  - Rolt, David (artist, did portrait of Ernie O'Malley), 1947, undated; cuid36670 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Rookh, Lalla, 1932; cuid36671 (Box 4, Folder 77)